Hello, welcome everyone. Hi, it is
Greetings. It's May 23rd, 2025 and we're
in active inference guest stream
109.1 with Alexander Heming presenting
some shared work on emotional attention
and predictive processing. So,
Alexander, thank you for joining.
looking forward to your presentation and
anyone watching live please feel free to
write questions in the live chat during
so thank you Alex too
okay sweet so emotional attention and
predictive processing um for the actual
uh presentation I'll go through an
introduction a foundations of
attentional narrowing then a
understanding of the neurology and a
connection between the attentional
narrowing and the predictive processing
uh I'll run through some computational
models so it'll give a more holistic
understanding of this and then we'll go
through a discussion which will include
the applications and future
directions. So this is the team. Um at
the moment I've got uh me uh there's a
co-author for a book I'm writing as well
called Dylan and then there's Kirsten
who is a psychology researcher at the
University of
Birmingham. So this is a project that
we're working on. I'm going to briefly
talk about this. This is a a book that
me and Dylan are working on. We're using
predictive processing and active
inference to understand the basis for
how ideologies are formed uh kind of
from a foundational way building up to
pretty much all the differences in
politics but it's it's difficult to go
into at this point. Uh if anyone has any
questions about this happy to answer as
well. Um so uh introducing the
idea.
Uh here we have the whole idea which is
in a sense uh when you have uh a
prediction and the prediction error uh
goes wrong about something which is very
emotional then you tend to have an
emotional salience of uh attentional
narrowing. So the threat uncertainty
creates a predictive error minimization
process but that also creates a neurom
modulation of a temperature parameter
which then creates a narrowing effect.
So you consider fewer
alternatives. Uh the thesis aims are to
kind of create more of a unified
understanding of the brain by adding
together more of an understanding of
what the actual parameters in the active
inference uh equations link to. It's
connecting it between a lot of different
disciplines to try and understand more
of how this this works. Uh a effect
based attention is one of the most prime
parts of this. It's uh how does
emotionally salient information go
through a basian distribution to try and
make a a different precision waiting
compared to more calculated predictions
which is the normal direction of
predictive
processing. The research gap is is
predominantly about the lack of a link
between processes such as dominant
response facilitation and attentional
narrowing and active inference. And so
using those two together, it it it aims
at addressing things which have not
really been talked about, but also
connecting a lot of this
together. I'm running through quite a
lot because we have quite a few slides
in the time, but the
foundation. So uh it starts originally
in the 1908 theory of the Jüks Dodson
inverse Ugraph, which many people might
know from Alevel psychology. Uh well
that's a UK thing but uh yeah and the
idea is that if you have a certain
amount of pressure then your most
reinforced responses will be
facilitated. So let's say you're playing
piano in front of an audience and you've
been practicing for a very long time
you'll actually improve your performance
of playing the piano until the stress
gets so high that you choke and you do
even worse than you did before. This
went on
to be understood by Easterbrook as uh
not just all arousal creates that. It's
not excitement which creates this
attentional daring process, but it's
actually a negative effect for it. So,
it's the uncertainty of some form of
threat will then create a form of
pressure. This form of pressure then
facilitates a uh lack of consideration
to alternatives. It's kind of automatic
when it goes into dominant response
facilitation, but he also connects it to
belief formation. It's almost like a
societal stress then facilitates a lack
of um consideration of alternatives when
you're creating an ideology or a uh
belief about certain concepts. Uh I've
included a few references in the slides
if anyone is interested. There's quite a
few more references but uh some of them
are a bit
key. Um so why hierarchal predictive
processing? Uh uh well this is uh more
about the idea that it kind of like
connects these things in a way where we
can actually add to more of a predictive
understanding of the brain as a whole.
It allows for a significant
uh magnitude between uh interaction
between the social phenomena and the
predictive mechanisms. So anything which
is dependent on motivational mechanisms
has more of a uh ingrained understanding
of it.
Um uh so that's the
uh attentional narrowing and now we've
got the neuroscience behind it which is
uh one one thing which is very strongly
researched is the neural gain and
emotions as computations perspective. uh
we do know that having uh adrenaline in
your system it's a kind of a neurom
modulator for these sorts of processes
and it does create this uh what what
I'll show later to be the sigmoid
function where the most reinforced the
the most reinforced processes are are
strengthened and the uh the other ones
which are more uh the you have a lower
probability of transitioning into these
states is reduced
Um so this is also enhanced by
prefrontal cortical inhibition. So we do
know that uh cortisol and uh
catakolamines do uh increase the
reactive to the the reflexive type of
actions and they reduce the uh
contemplative reflexive uh thought
processes. This means that when you are
under a lot of stress, it's it's
difficult to contemplate and think
clearly, but it's quite easy to react to
sudden in uh situations and do the most
learned and most reinforced behaviors.
But it's more of an effective
neuroscience look at things because it's
opening and closing different pathways
rather than something which is more
ingrained in the computational
neuroscience of seeing how excitable
different neurons are such as which
would happen in the neural game. So it's
instead of resistance to uh stocastic
resonance and noise which affects each
individual neuron it would be more of a
opening and closing of different
pathways but it still has the same
effect of the attentional narrowing
mechanism. Um as we can see from
reflexive it's more about the individual
contemplative strategies of the
individual.
Um and as we can see from the reflexive,
it's more about the reaction
processes. It's uh it it's more of a
slow acting process uh when we have uh
kind of adrenaline rushing into our
system and it affects the entire brain.
So this is different to uh direct
precision racing which you would
normally see inside policy se selection
mechanisms because you have this idea
that there's a uh different exploration
exploitation uh dynamic in which you
kind of focus on the things which are
the most expected to happen. They become
more salient and when something
unexpected happens about these most
expected situations then you you kind of
focus on that and then you dive into
that type of information. That's such a
a specific dynamical process that it's
not something you consider as
universally affecting all areas of the
brain in a very uh emergent way where
you have an individual neuron uh and the
traits with those neurons actually
affecting the dynamics of how the whole
brain works. It's more about the actual
processes of how free energy works in
the brain.
Um so stress from prediction
error emotional veilance is the way in
which you would kind of understand
stress to come about. This is if you
have a negative emotional veilance then
you would have an emotion which does not
uh it's not pleasant. It's it's
something which is kind of like fear um
anger uh sadness. These are all negative
emotions. And because of the least
action principle, people go down the
idea of you want to avoid the negatives
and you want to reduce the amount of
energy the reduce the amount of free
energy. So uh all negatives were
associated with a rate of change
increase with free energy. But the issue
with that was when people use the idea
of predictive error minimization, they
tend to uh use the idea of everyone is
always predicting everything and
everything has to be a direct
calculation. And that has been an issue.
Uh the kind of like rationalizations
people go about that is like a uh if
you're surprised by a present which a
friend has given you. It has filled the
prediction of a social expectation of
you being given a present. Um it doesn't
necessarily have to be that type of
rationalization but you can see how
these things don't seem to have much
intuitive sense behind them. And that's
that's why when we have uh Joffly's um
points we we delve into the idea of like
when there's a prediction and it has an
uh you predicted something but it
becomes worse to you than what you
originally predicted then that is still
something you would say has negative
emotional veilance and that's a very
simple way of thinking about us but it
still works in the way of even though
it's a negative to what you actually
predicted it is still an increase in
free energy or predictive error mechan
mechisms because you can understand that
prediction might not be the best word
for this and a few people have written
articles on this. Uh one
person has decided to determine that
it's a uh instead of basian prior they
say a basian uh preference. So it's a a
basian prior distribution and a basian
preference distribution. If we have the
basian prior distribution, we can have
the idea that there is a calculated
waiting of what you expect to happen
based on your uh kind of like uh prior
uh opinion of that being that
probability and it's very calculative.
It's very much on this understanding of
what is observed is is real and you're
trying to get round to what is actually
an accurate representation of things.
But if you have certain sensory inputs
and they might just be like, uh, I'm
hungry. I need this. And as as if people
know about the dark room, uh, situation,
that doesn't always add up in the way
that
people understand how motivation works
in in the way that prediction is is
accounting for the the the hunger. And
instead you kind of would have to have a
a preference distribution a basian
preference distribution which can be
understood more instead of as
predictions more as uh desires and
drives which then weights the predictive
mechanisms towards a certain direction.
But this at the lower order uh
functioning would still be
uh would still be kind of a a basian
prior in of itself because it's it's
having an influence in the uh
probability distribution to try and give
you more probability to weighting your
behavior in that direction. So it
shouldn't really be understood as a
basian prior prediction but more as a a
driving force which increases salience
of certain
ideas. And this this leads into what uh
my co-author and uh colleague in in the
article uh uh is keen on describing as a
human vs can't uh dynamic and the canian
understanding of predictive processing
is very much on their way of
understanding the generative model. But
it does ignore the fundamental idea that
you can understand to a certain degree a
relationship between desires and
passions directing what you want as an
individual. Uh they the fundamental
thing is in a sense would you do
anything if you didn't have a desire to
move a desire to exist a desire to do
everything? Uh or are you a method for
the universe to know itself and you're
just an emergent property which has
calculations uh for the sake of it. It
it doesn't make sense without there
being a driving force which does count
as the concept of a desire and these
desires in a basian preference
distribution can direct individuals uh
behaviors and uh even their beliefs
towards uh things that are important to
them. Uh attentional narrowing in
predictive processing. So as intentional
narrowing uh relates to all this you can
see that as uh you have a uh couple
basian preferences and basian prize and
they're in uh dissonance with each other
there's predictive error because of the
uh mismatch between these two and that
can create the negative emotional
veilance. This negative emotional
veilance can then stimulate a neurom
modulation of a attentional narrowing
process which then affects the way that
your decisions would be made. They
attentionally narrow you. So you have
less exploration to alternatives, thus
making your decisions, especially in in
societal uncertainty, a bit more rigid,
a bit more deterministic and a bit more
going down uh reinforced certain
paths and this leads into the
exploration exploitation trade-off.
Going further into the mathematics, we
can understand that there is a a
tendency to explore a lot of
alternatives or a tendency to uh exploit
the very well- learned and very uh
deterministic paths. And this is
understood differently by uh according
to different paths. But we've got the
fundamental variable in predictive
processing that relates to cognitive
rigidity and attentional narrowing and
that is the omega value. This is a
stress induced sigmoid version function.
It that means it's a it's a temperature
parameter but an inverse of that. So one
over the temperature parameter. What
happens is we could know it is affecting
all processes
uh equally as as this as this. If if
there was the same sigmoid function for
every neuron, then you know if there's
the same excitability of every neuron,
then that would be termed as the sigmoid
function because it is the same uh the
the most reactive uh would be more
reactive and more reliable and the least
reactive would be the the less reliable
uh making the the pathways a lot more
deterministic. And it it shows for
example in Nashal we have the
understanding of how relationship
uncertainty can create uh political
absolutism. And this is you you can see
how inside a precision waiting mechanism
that shouldn't be the case. It shouldn't
be that uh you've had something with a
relationship. So you're going to become
more absolutist in an ideological
perspective. they they don't relate to
each other, but somehow one of them
affects the other, which can only really
be understood outside of precision
waiting in a more domain agnostic kind
of perspective, though I don't think I'm
using that term necessarily
correctly. Um, sorry. Uh, so inverse
temperature, just to run through what
this is, it's it's the uh thing in
thermodynamics where the more atoms you
are hitting, the higher the temperature.
Thus the more uh uh the higher a
temperature you have the more attention
you are paying to the the the less
narrowed your attention. And following
that you can see that uh that uh there
is um a sigmoid function would then
reduce the temperature because it would
make everything go down uh a very linear
path. uh you would only have the well
rehearsed well-learned things which are
going to be exploited rather than the
directions which would be a lot more
chaotic. It's almost as though the the
chaos can add to like uh in the edge of
chaos perspective we have a optimal
functioning where we have the most
exploration uh bordering on chaos with
actually having the largest amount of
complexity within a system which still
has a function behind it.
cognitive flexibility as the baseline
parameter. This is uh the equation that
we brought in uh which is the idea that
uh the rate of change of free energy uh
times by a uh ability to handle
dissonance
uh uh minus or added to the initial
cognitive rigidity of an individual
makes the uh attentional narrowed
cognitive rigidity. And this parameter
then can be used in the state change
function. It it reflects cognitive
flexibility in a number of different
fields because you can see how a lot of
people in certain uh psychopathological
diagnosis diagnoses can uh do tend to
have cognitive inflexibility in a way
which would support this
uh
equation. And in the computational
models we have the state change uh state
transition temperature. So this one here
is the the the main equation. Uh it's
obviously not mine but there's the uh
the omega value here which you can see
times by the logarithm of the uh
transition matrices which is uh the uh
the next stage considering what the
current stage is. And so uh when you
have the log of all these values then
you're pushing them which the high ones
to the high point and the low ones to
the low point and then you're creating a
softmax function to guide these all to
add up to one and that kind of allows
them to be accurately mapped out inside
a uh probability distribution or
uh and this then makes the transformed
uh uh transformed matrices afterwards.
Um, sorry. And here's to go through the
maths. If anyone wants to pause it on
here, it might be a bit better, but I
think I I went through the maths just
[Music]
then. Um, and here we can see when we
combine this all together. So, the
probability of the next stage
considering the previous stage is equal
to the soft max of this, which is the
original equation that we came up with
for determining how the negative
veilance affects
uh a new uh attentional narrating
process. And this attentional narrowed
uh original omega v variable then is
multiplied by the logarithm of the uh
transition m transaction
matrix when and as you can see when it
is uh low uh then this is the maximum
amount of cognitive flexibility. This is
when you can have a very clear mind and
consider all the possibilities before
you. But you may have choice paralysis.
You may uh not be very comfortable in a
fight orflight situation where the
pressure of a situation is making you uh
go to a sudden immediate action which is
going to be the most learned action and
you want to do it very well. And uh when
you have it as deterministically as
possible, even simple thoughts might be
difficult because you might need to
explore uh a lot of options around you
and and even the most deterministic
thing could just be to stand there and
be frozen in the
headlights. As such, uh this affects
both belief formation and dominant
response formation because we can we can
see how this affects every aspect of of
of life uh in in in our interests. it's
in politics but uh obviously it does it
does reflect in psychopathology and it
does reflect in sport
psychology. This uh leads to the
biirectional dance of cognitive
rigidity. So we do have the idea that um
from the ground upwards so from the
sensing to the actual thoughts we have
how the environment affects the brain
and that would be uh the stresses inside
the environment and that's in the
bottomup processes. So as we are in any
societal uncertainty, it will create
these prediction errors. And when these
prediction errors are are manifest, they
will then lower the uh temperature
parameter which then top down goes to
your actions which are to have more
entrenched reinforced beliefs and it is
to have uh a limited you you may jump to
conclusions more easily. You may be
fixated on certain points. You have an
inability to change your mind about
certain things. And you would also be
more likely to do your well practiced
responses rather than exploring
alternatives. This leads to
discussion. Right? So
uh flexible minds nuance their ideas.
This is uh this is something I find
quite quite uh interesting in in this
concept. So if we have this inability to
transition from one state to another
state then we don't really have the
ability to consider other people's
perspectives to add to and build on our
ideas. If we entrench ourselves in our
ideas, if we have rigid minds, if we
have absolutist ideologies, if we have
absolute things inside any any
perspective, then we are unable to uh
create the most complicated the most
detailed uh concepts which you know in
this leading to this uh ultimate
complexity at the edge of chaos. It
would never be achievable if we stick
ourselves in what would be a uh which I
should have addressed as a sub-optimal
local minima uh in a sense of if we
imagine a large landscape of of ideas
and we can't explore other places and we
can't get out of this hole of an idea
we're in then we will never see a bigger
hole of an idea which is a better hole.
Uh we would have to get to the globally
best hole. uh we would always be stuck
in um the the rigid beliefs which can
potentially lead to a lot of problems.
Whereas uh having flexible nuance
beliefs means we will have more
integrated complexity in our ideas. In
political theory that is how you get to
the best conclusions. It's not
necessarily that there's one idea which
is better than another idea. It's just
if you get an absolutist idea, you tend
to have problematic stances on on a
multitude of different things. It's it's
uh better to consider as many
perspectives as possible so you're aware
of good ideas. But I believe there's a
famous quote of uh it's good to have an
open mind but not so open your brain
falls out. But um there are a lot of a
lot of nuances to every aspect and every
rule that you can make both for yourself
and for everything in in
society. And this is in conjunction with
cognitive dissonance and predictive
processing. you can have uh an
integration more more thoroughly with
this based off the attentional narrowing
details. So as we have basian prize uh
something important to you is criticized
which is in the basian preference
distribution and that in conjunction
with basian pride distribution of of
calculations can then uh create uh the
the resolutions in cognitive dissonance
and these resolutions are either uh a
effects um cognitions or behaviors. So
these are the ideas in cognitive
dissonance which are in contradiction
with each other which cause the
dissonance which causes the res
rationalizations which make the theory
of cognitive dissonance. Uh and so if
you have an emotional uh pointer it
could be an addiction to cigarettes and
then you have a fact of cigarettes are
bad for you. um this dissonance between
them creates a prediction error and this
prediction error then leads you to
rationalize that uh cigarettes will help
you lose weight or cigarettes will do
these are these are common cult
scenarios uh studied quite quite well
but that that establishes how when you
have attentional narrowing your
consideration of alternatives reduced to
such a degree that you're more likely to
rationalize because it lowers your
ability to see alternatives is as you
move towards the rationalization making
the rationalizations
more distinct when things are very
emotionally significant to
you. Um and this leads connected to
heristic adherance. So uh heristic
adherance is very strongly connected to
uh uh cognitive dissonance to a degree
and uh the predictive processing
mechanisms because heruristics um if you
read the Daniel Conorman thing that
they're generally held in negative light
but heristics are are also often held
inside just a tool for how you can do
things throughout life. But if you are
attentionally narrowed, then your
heristic adurance is a lot stronger
because uh to get out of your entrenched
beliefs, you have to rely on something
which is kind of an easy go-to card. And
this uh this can mean that uh you
are unlikely to uh nuance these
heruristics. Um if you don't nuance your
heristics however then you tend to
justify perspectives in society which uh
to a lot of people can seem very clearly
wrong but if you're under a very large
amount of emotional strain then it can
seem more appealing to you. Um an
obvious horistic which was studied in in
marketing is the price tag. you rely on
the price tag and but if you're really
stressed, you don't really know what to
think and you're kind of faced with this
time pressure, then the price tag itself
will be a reliance you'll have on the
actual value of the item you are buying.
But then you also have uh one of my
favorite uh heruristics well one of the
worst heristics but that I like to talk
about is uh the just world
fallacy/hypothesis and this is generally
defined as uh everybody gets what they
deserves and deserves what they get. In
this perspective we have a justification
for the status quo which uh you know
could could be anything inside the most
authoritarian of societies. It can be uh
very distinct uh cultural dynamics which
you feel you can't see why they happen
but you're going to justify them because
they exist for a reason because they
exist. And this can cause a lot of
victim blaming. It can cause uh the
belief in a pretender fallacy. If you're
in a situation where you do not feel
like you deserve this and you do feel
you feel like something is not right
about things, it can be due to a
backfire with a seristic. It can uh be
in the general resistance to change
which uh is endemic with uh uh the loss
aversion tendency because people are
generally against change even when it's
beneficial and a just world hypothesis
attaches onto that because the heristic
adurance to the idea that everything
must make sense or you know it it exists
for a reason makes you unlikely to
change especially when there is a lot of
stress. So the attentional narrowing
mechanism uh facilitates the predictive
processing error minimization which
causes more of reliance on the huristics
which then reduce your ability to change
in these situations and this is very
strongly studied in relation to
cognitive rigidity uh through how
cognitive rigidity is a fundamental
neuroscientific trait. It's more recent
in the developments of political
psychology, but it shows that cognitive
fragility helps uh or forces people to
be unable to change their mind and to
create what they term as absolutist
ideologies. So, does this better our
understanding of the brain? I think
combining attentional narrowing with co
uh cognitive rigidity and putting them
into a computational mechanism within
the uh active inference models of state
transitions does help give an
understanding of the brain which
enhances the predictive processing
mechanisms and it's should help uh
enhance uh every every uh step of its
involvement with the the uh in
involvement in in psychop ology in
precision psychiatry because it it uh if
you go into the area of psychology the
the importance of how stress affects
people is is incredibly significant and
showing if there's biological components
to this whether they can be reinforced
or not. Uh some innate component which
is outside of the direct environment
which makes a difference between people
is also interesting for the diagnostic
criteria of what people go
through. And that's where we get into
the applications
uh precision psychiatry. Um so
schizophrenics and autistics um tend to
have uh more uh cognitive rigidity. They
tend to be uh cognitively inflexible is
what they term it. But uh the resistance
to changing their beliefs and the
correlation they've had uh has actually
led people to even ask the question of
is cognitive flexibility the missing
link? Is it the component in in the uh
differences between people which which
cause the genetic component? Uh because
the genetic markers for autism and
schizophrenia are vaguely strong and so
the link between these two uh is is seen
to be on the cognitive fragility which
seem to be strong in both categories.
uh inside predictive processing. People
have also had the idea of uh the
generative model and the recognition
model being quite significant in how uh
uh the generative model and the
over-the-top uh focus on predictions and
uh imagination of the scenario creates
the preference for schizophrenic people
to have hallucinations and uh delusions
and come up with ideas outside of uh
what people would normally expect to be
realistic. And in the autistic
situation, there's the sensory overload
which is more in the sensory uh aspect
of the recognition model. And that's uh
over focus on the sensory information.
Uh seems to be more in there seems to be
a very large link between um autism and
schizophrenia according to the
disregulation perspectives of uh acts of
inference. And that is why there's a
relevance to schizophrenia because it uh
it really the the idea of the uh the
entrenching in beliefs is is is strong
with the concept of delusions. So
schizophrenics are also more likely to
have conspiracy theories. And this
entrenched belief system that they hold
means that the cognitive rigidity uh
appears to be a strong factor in what
develops the problematic uh uh issues
with with the diagnosis
uh with suffering with
schizophrenia. There is also educational
benefits. So there are studies into the
idea of uh just attentional narrowing in
general increasing your focus and if you
have a certain amount of pressure then
it does help you study harder. Um this
is importance in a lot of a lot of
developments in psychology which can use
the concepts of attentional narrowing
especially in a mechanistic way to uh
develop into other psychological
concepts which then help understand how
uh a drive towards supporting a value
and ideal you believe in can be
facilitated by the pressure of this
ideal. It is almost as though when you
have a bit of stress in your life
sometimes laser focusing on a task can
reduce that stress. Doing something
which you uh is associated with your
values can reduce a
uh error process. A it can do an error
minimization mech uh mechanism for for
the actual issues at
hand. And uh this also can understand
how learned helplessness can happen from
a error minimization process where uh
you see what you are doing as being
uh difficult to solve. So instead of uh
when the when the attentional narrowing
gets too high, you will go down to a
simpler solution which is learned
helplessness or giving up or
disassociating from the concept instead
of uh focusing on the task. The anxiety
will get too high and it'll be harder to
focus on that task. And understanding
that inside a uh relationship between
other metrics inside the brain can help
understand what can cause learned
helplessness and what influences can
develop that. Further uh a respect for
academia academia in in total can
facilitate the uh importance waiting and
the
uh basian prior distributions in favor
of uh doing better in academia. And it
can actually uh according to certain
texts for example the book the moral arc
uh there's there's evidence that respect
for academia and having a skeptic first
mindset can facilitate a sense of
morality in any country which holds
those
values which I think is quite
significant and future research
directions after the
applications. This uh is in social and
political psychology. These are areas in
which I think attentional narrowing and
cognitive rigidity are are profound.
Obviously, cognitive rigidity is is
pretty good for cognitive rigidity. If
we have a computational aspect of that
and we attach it to the mechanisms of of
uh
of predictive processing, then it will
distinctly help. uh right-wing the
right-wing authoritarian personality
trait which is uh a uh kind of it's it's
a development from something which is
called the fascist scale which applies
to both the far left inside a
traditionally left country and the far
right in a traditionally right-wing
country most of all u but it's still
called right-wing authoritarianism
because of the associated of right-wing
with traditional conventional attitudes
and that being correlated with the
concept of authoritarianism.
Social dominance orientation is is kind
of the idea of feeling as though there
should be a dominance over certain
groups. And all of these seem to
associate with the concept of heruristic
adherance in the political environment.
It's it's the adherance to rules, the
idea that everyone gets what it deserves
and does what they get because of this
authoritarian structure that you live
in. Um that enhances by the intentional
narrowing focus. And as such you can
kind of see how they would not nuance
their beliefs according to these
dynamics of their society and they would
go more absolutist into supporting of
any ideological background especially
when it's strongly associated with a
basian preference and that uh that works
for all of these all of these processes
and they're all uh uh psychology
theories which are very interesting and
in social psychology you can see how
they also relate in the same way. Uh
game theory I'm not the most certain on
but social facilitation is is the basic
one about dominant response
facilitation. Uh conformity under stress
obviously would increase because you
have the uncertainty enhancing the
attentional narrowing even though it's
not directly precision weighted. There's
uh there's uh the threat uncertainty
significantly influences your chance to
conform. And even in the Dunning Krueger
effect, uh there's a uh preference to
narrowing your focus to only what you've
experienced and not to an exploration of
unknown profits. And so uh this this
process is believing you're better than
you are because you don't have much
experience about what else is out there,
which probably happens in the area of
research and I'm hoping doesn't happen
to be too much. But uh I I think that
there's the idea of exploring other
options instead of going down your
singular path which which gives you more
an awareness of the unknown
unknowns. And then there's reactive
approach motivation. So this is
something which I think is a really good
uh direction to take future research
after attentional narrowing cuz this
gives more of a holistic picture of uh
how cult how when under stress you will
do certain things which then make you
more zealous. Um it's uh I have a I have
a quote here which is uh if any adaptive
change in the brain uh will minimize
free energy then how does an adaption to
stress minimize free energy and the
adaption to stress doesn't always
minimize free energy in in in that in
that regard it aims to minimize free
energy but because of the positive
feedback loop it can loop things through
quite a lot and in the way that reactive
approach and vation tries to react to
stress reactive approach motivation is
that they find that any societal
stressors will uh be reduced by
disassociation from these societal
stressors through a laser focus in an
ideal that you believe in. You can
distract yourself by focusing on
something which to you has value and
worth. And that does increase for
example uh zealous adherance to a
cult-like religion um in opposition to
when you are suffering quite a lot in a
lot of threat and certainty in your
personal life and that can be enhanced
by cognitive fragility when maybe the
stresses are more
effective. And
uh then this is the conclusion summary
of points. So from this we've got
attentional narrowing from emotional uh
uh stresses. Uh this creates uh the
predictive error minimization from uh uh
emotional stresses uh creates a increase
of rate of change of free energy which
then uh forces you
to rely on on huristics to when when
your attention is narrowed and you are
too rigid inside your perspectives
because you you then don't nuance these
huristics and then you have a
perspective on both society and actions
in society.
as well as a facilitation of uh of more
learned like uh practiced piano
responses in front of an audience type
of situations of uh the the most
reinforced neural connections and belief
formations and belief that you don't
really have belief updating. Sorry. Uh
and it develops a more authoritarian
outlook on things in society.
And thanks and if you have any questions
then you can email me and uh also you
can ask for the email of either of my
colleagues well mostly Dylan and uh Mr.
Grove and it would uh be much
appreciated.
Thank you Alexander. So Daniel yes
awesome thank you. Um, while I'm
cropping things back, maybe share a
little bit like how did you come to this
project or how did you come together
with these authors and what are you like
looking for in terms of milestones in
that collaboration?
Um, uh, well, I I've I've, uh, been the
co-author with Dylan for for a while and
we've been writing a book which is the
the foundations of ideology. So our our
our our work in in trying to you know
explain the political dynamics we came
to quite a lot of conclusions about
things when we did research very
continuously coming up with a lot of
ideas and and in our research we've
we've read quite a few books on on
between us on on active inference and
there seems to be a very prominent gap
uh uh what I what I hope to gain from it
is to add to the community and to try
and help as much as possible uh well to
to ingrain myself in inside research and
uh uh well the the book has been uh my
passion project for for a while now and
it's uh and it's now Dylan's passion
project to a degree as well and uh we do
believe that this will uh be good to add
to the research community and it will
help the world in the theory of how you
know you can address certain things
which will help a lot of people inside a
diagnosis and in political dynamics
reducing in the polarization of the
world for example. So
okay, lot of topics that we could go
into. Um there's a few questions in the
live chat and anyone can ask more
questions. So I'll read some of those.
Um maybe leave the slides up and we
could go to a slide if it comes up.
Okay. Um all right. Susan asks, "Is
there any research on addiction to
exploitation?" Um, yes. Yeah. I mean
there well addiction to exploitation uh
well the exploitation exploration
trade-off is more of a machine learning
term but uh the the
the thing about addiction is is actually
more towards the uh the policy selection
process and that's that's uh not the
state transition process necessarily and
that addiction mechanism is more about
uh kind of the gamma temperature
variable rather than the omega
temperature variable and it's It's it's
kind of more about uh uh the the
dopamine pathways and how you are uh
reinforced into having I I I'm not I'm
not super knowledgeable about that area,
but I know it's it's more associated
with dopamine. It's more associated with
policy selection rather than state
transition. And there is a lot of
research on
that from what I'm aware.
Okay, here's a a question that I wrote
down. Well, first the scope is very
vast essentially encompassing our human
cognitive niche ranging from differences
in neurodeiversity associated with like
context changes and different scenarios
in a given day-to-day life to just
different people different stages of
life and then all the way into these
social pieces. So Mhm. H how how do we
think about these more system
general cognitive phenomena with the
domain specific phenomena and then also
multistep kind of like rhetorical or
justification phenomena like what do you
think that model kind of looks like? The
equations do give some pointers and
reference, but what what do you see the
puzzle pieces coming together looking
like to bring to together like
fundamental constraints of
informationational systems with these
system general stress and attention
phenomena with ultimately the kind of
domain specific models that are usually
deployed in a specific generative model.
Yeah. Well, I I mean I think the the
specific generative models can work the
best uh uh as as they are. And then this
this uh this model just basically goes
that when you explore in a sense in in
any part of in any part of the marov
chain, you are also forcing on yourself
more of a rate of change of free energy.
It's it's almost like uh any action that
is taken will theoretically in their
increase of free energy, they will
potentially create stress. It's it's
like thinking in a like if you were
playing chess, you would force yourself
to feel stressed just to try and solve a
puzzle. And that forcing yourself to
feel stressed means you are creating a
tiny bit of stress which then narrows
your thought processes. So it's not that
it's it's that this stuff happens
anyway, but there's very constraining
mechanisms in place which just stop too
much free energy accumulating during
that same domain specific process. if
the domain specific processes are are
specific to to going along one direction
from one step to another in a mark of
chain rather than in a uh one thing
affects everything dynamic.
Thanks. Yeah, that was one of the parts
I found most interesting uh in sort of
the deep affective work and the way that
you brought it out and and worked it
here is like the re-entry of the rate of
change of free energy into an equation
cuz otherwise the the free energy values
or the rates of change can be
essentially epipenomenal like a model
diagnostic used in training but then
that generative model doesn't have
re-entry or causal efficacy of the free
energy itself. But then it is this
really clever way to bring global
dynamics back into the process of the
domain. Like staying with that chess
example, there's a time pressure and
time pressure and choosing when to act
is not always modeled in decision-m
models. it'll just be this kind of like
frozen universe and then a slot machine
is pulled or a frozen universe and then
a move is made in a teammates. So then
when you start to bring in the the
unfolding
dynamics, it's it's this kind of like
everything plays into that free energy
value or rate of change and that
provides the domain
agnostic
signal of basically how well things are
going and then veilance has been
associated with whether that is going
better or worse than itself was expected
to be.
Yeah. Yeah. Perfect. I like the analogy.
Um, okay. Another question from Susan.
Could cognitive rigidity be related to a
deficit in perceptual affordance acuity?
Um, I think I think perceptual processes
are are are a different neurom
modulator. uh in in the way in which I
got the uh the the the state transition
from from a 2024 article uh there was a
a uh aelco or aelcholine um uh parameter
for for uh for perception specifically
um I'm not too keen on on the knowledge
of perception but I do know that there
is in that area something more it's a
different neurom
modulator that's that's as far as I can
go I I I do think that when you look at
neurotransmitters and hormones inside
the brain there is a tendency for um uh
neurotransmitters to slightly affect
other pathways. If if you look at how
stochastic resonance which is the noise
between neurotransmitters affect each
other. It's not necessarily that uh you
have to have the the thing which is
normally activated by that
neurotransmitter is only activated by
that. There's like a slight effect from
others. So I think adrenaline could
affect your vision as well. But I think
it's more about the the the ability to
change your states inside those
processes. So I I I I don't know too
much about that
area.
H okay. On uh I think it was
slide
30. Is that 30? Oh, wait. No, I'm
getting the wrong way. Cool.
Okay. Yes.
Yes. All
right. So, maximum cognitive
flexibility is being associated with a
uniform probability distribution over
future
states. So,
um yeah, that's that's not true
really temperature.
Sorry. Well, it can't it can't be a
uniform obviously. There's it's it's
almost just that there's a temperature
parameter adding in which is making you
more rigid and only more rigid. It
doesn't it doesn't ever go in the
opposite direction. I mean there there
is the idea that if you are happier
about things then you are actually more
cognitively flexible and there are there
are studies which show that but uh I I
don't think it can ever get to a uniform
perspective. That's just a theoretical
perspective of uh you know if if you
have temperature and you put it in
different directions. If I could see
that in anywhere uh of of of an actual
possibility, I would basically think
there's someone stuck in one place
unable to make any decision about
anything because they're trying to see
everything with equal possibility. And
it's it's kind of like when you have the
edge of chaos concept. So you have the
ordered structure overfitting and then
you have the uh over exploration
actually into chaos. You know, you'll
have strange attractors, you'll have
other things, but it's it's it's not
really information. It's not information
in in a in enough of a structured way to
mean anything in a goal-directed way. It
it is just chaos. And anyone who is
actually pushed to that point of
exploration, they would not be able to
have any structured beliefs and they
would de devolve to
chaos. But it would probably be closer
to a praasia. It would be the sense of
like a you know you you wouldn't have
hallucinations or anything because if
you have that much chaos a hallucination
is still a structured dynamic process
where you have idea to idea idea. It's
almost a hallucination I would say is
more rigid because you can't escape the
hallucination even if you want to. Um
whereas uh this would be more you can't
even have a simple thoughts because
you're considering so many
possibilities. You're completely
changing all the time.
That's the way I think of think of it
really.
Yes. Interesting. So the more rigidity
is just crystallizing or just sharpening
the
definition on a given on the given
contours of a belief. In this situation,
it's a belief about the consequences of
action.
Um the the rigidity I feel like belief
is is a oh wait sorry so the wait sorry
what is the belief? Um well the B matrix
are beliefs about how things are apt to
change conditioned upon what actions are
taken.
Yeah. Um well I was thinking more in in
a distribution of beliefs which are
uh going to trigger other beliefs in the
future. So if you have a basian prior
which is uh kind of like a if it's
creating an attractive dynamic of flow
into a certain direction then what's the
chance of that happening considering
those chances but then if you multiply
that by temperature then you would
potentially make it more rigid and not
transition into the next stage
um so sorry can you repeat the question
one one more time
I I I'm just trying to to work out what
is being made more rigid did in the B
matrix and so
well it's it would be beliefs are more
rigid um in in terms of dominant
response facilitation it would be uh you
are being made more rigid in your your
it's it's the fluid dynamics in the
brain of information. So the the
rigidity would be the attractive
dynamic. It would be in a sense the
information flowing throughout the brain
is going through a singular path. And
because it's going through that singular
path, that means that you're uh not
going
to uh have more uh uh different options
that you're considering. You're going to
only have the
uh uh singular dynamic of of playing the
the piano inside that one direction. But
uh in in a belief it would be that you
would having more rigid beliefs it would
be uh you have more entrenched beliefs
being facilitated more which means that
when someone is trying to convince you
of an idea and your beliefs are very
entrenched and you're under attentional
narrowing then the chance that your
belief will change will be very
minimal. I think yeah I I I think I hear
you and it may be interesting to parse
out flexibility as the capacity to
change from flexibility being the
sharpness of a given distribution in a
moment because you could have a very
sharp belief distribution about
successor of the next states or whatever
it happens to be and that could be
rapidly changing. or it could be fixed.
And then you could have sort of uh um
closer to a flatter distribution that
also could be
changing, but there's less room for
change the flatter you get. With this
extreme case like you brought up, it's
like, yeah, does a blob have
flexibility? It's like it doesn't even
have enough differentiation to have
flexibility cuz it's just sort of inert.
Um question from live chat. Yeah. What
did you mean by temperature? That's a
great question.
Uh temperature uh well it came from
thermodynamics. So in in the
understanding of temperature in
thermodynamics you have more uh entropy
which is more information happening. So,
so when I mean temperature, it's it's
it's uh originally the the term of just
uh more stuff happening and then it in
this it's used uh in the normal kind of
reinforcement learning equations of the
amount of
uh options being considered. So, so in
in this it is uh when you when you
multiply it by the the the matrix which
is the amount of coordinates in a graph
which are pointing in a specific
direction. So it's like a vector
database. If you imagine, sorry, it's if
you if you imagine uh weather and
convection currents in weather, they are
pushing air in one direction. And if
you're mapping out a still image of this
weather, you'll have arrows moving in
different directions from where the
convection currents are pushing things.
You can then give numbers to all of
these arrows. So all of these arrows are
kind of like points inside this graph.
And when when you have these these uh
sorry when you have these points in
these graphs, you can give them numbers.
And sorry, this is getting uh way too
complicated, but but um these numbers
then represent the the amount of uh push
inside a given direction and the
probability of it going in that
direction. And if you put this into a
probability distribution like in in
quantum mechanics, it represents the
same thing as in fluid dynamics and
inside graphing temperature convection
currents. Uh sorry. And and uh then the
probability of uh one thing moving from
one thing to another thing is going to
be uh like 10 or two uh and maybe higher
or lower. But if it's a high probability
then the temperature being uh lower
means that sorry so that's the point
when you have temperature lower uh the
high probability is raised in its number
when you have temperature higher that
when you have temperature lower also the
the lower probability is made
lower sorry I'm not really in the best
of zones for this but but temperature
adjusts the probability so it makes more
probable actions more likely and less
probable actions less likely
enough time using it in this. Yes. I
think about Kelvin, the temperature
scale, and how there's a basically a
stopping of molecular motion. And so if
we were to have a ball rolling on a
table and the table were to be unmoving
and we were to drop the ball on like one
way to say it is it would find the
lowest point or a little bit of a looser
way is it would reflect the actual
distribution of the hills and the
valleys and then as you shake it more
and more with higher temperature those
differences start to matter less in
elevation because there's so much energy
being added in by the movement of the
table that the small differences in in
elevation are are basically outweighed
by the random jostling.
Yeah. Um yeah, finding the local minima
through gradient descent. Yeah, it's a
good metaphor. Okay, another question
from and go. Yeah, go ahead then. I'll
ask another
question. No, sorry. I was just going to
say yeah. Oh, sorry. No, carry on,
please. Sorry.
Sorry. Go for it.
Uh so uh well I I would say I guess the
the only way to escape a one of those
dips is to add a bit of chaos into it
and that chaos can also be understood as
the temperature because it's not really
efficient to try and get out of a
correct answer which is the dip to find
a bigger
dip. So you have to have something which
is a bit chaotic like temperature.
Yeah. I I think the um way that you
brought in the U curve response is going
to be really interesting to see uh as
you develop this out because like that
reflective and and um reactive or those
on the previous
slide
stress may increase the uh piano playing
a little bit but then it doesn't it
doesn't have a monotonic relationship.
But then often times when we're working
with like a preference vector or
something like that just it's kind of
like you just increase the preference
just forever. So it's actually hard on
to bring in those U curve like
responses but those have a lot more
biological validity when we start
looking at the the tension between
different different general systems.
Yeah, that makes a lot of sense. If
there was a preference for for
something, I guess um any contradiction
to that would create more free energy,
which would then create more attentional
narrowing in that
regard. Okay, I'll ask a question from
the live
chat. Vtor wrote, could trends be
identified in real time or near real
time, do you think? I'm thinking of say
collecting personal data and
establishing a personal baseline.
Um uh I think uh that's more of
psychology research than this is
computational neuroscience. But you
could definitely you can definitely find
trends in in real time and you can
validate certain things based on uh
how likely someone is going to like if
you wait the importance someone has
towards a certain thing then it it can
it can definitely uh be be collected in
real time based off surveys and certain
bits of information. And then also you
can probably do like galvanic skin
response things to to check how uh much
aversive arousal or negative effect
someone will have and then see how their
attention will be narrowed towards that
especially when considering criticisms
to things which they hold very important
to them which would then be more more
entrenched beliefs and more
rationalization of these perspectives.
It's it's possible, but it's uh I I
don't think it's realistic and and it
doesn't really I don't I I think uh it
it's not based on this type of research
necessarily, but it is something which
is more based inside the theories it's
building towards in psychology
already. However, in these models,
you're talking about observables and
latent states of people. So, conceivably
that does connect with
some kind of self-report or biometric or
other behavioral measure that would be
used to parameterize the model. So what
would that look like and h how do you
see that being brought into
practice?
Um well uh I I think it's it's possible
but it it wouldn't be super accurate. Um
the kind of uh explanatory power of of
this process is is pretty good and you
can you can have some validity to it.
You could probably do some significance
test towards it. Um, but what you would
probably do is just copy uh Leor's
Migro's research on cognitive agility
where she finds that cognitive agility
through so card assortment tests
correlates with the absolutist ideology
and that then you can connect that to
some other people's research on
cognitive rigidity which is associated
with attentional narrowing and then if
if so these things are are quite well
established and then using the uh active
inference uh uh equations in in support
of that just more uh gives an
explanation for it rather than giving an
enhance to the predictive power of it.
um it can the the influence of uh
computational modeling with with all
these is probably beneficial and and if
you had EEG scans on people's heads you
could probably see the processes of
error minimization in conjunction with
this but uh it would it would probably
look very very close to the research by
Leor
Migro and and it probably wouldn't be
self-report either it would probably be
uh just uh I think it's implicit
cognitive fragility tasks that she does
most of the time. I don't think she
actually does much on on the self-report
side of things.
Okay, kind of zooming out a bit, how do
you think
ideology will evolve or change as
cognitive science brings new insights
into neuromchanistic aspects and real
time and different influences on
ideology because it's been I think as
your interdisciplinary approach is
showing there's like political analysis
of psychological analysis of so as these
puzzle pieces come together what is that
going to look like and what ideology
comes out of the wash there.
Yeah. Well, I mean, I I think uh there's
this tendency for people to always try
and point out gaps uh to try and support
a perspective that they'll have. And
this filling of all of the gaps gives a
gives a enough of a of a reasoning to
try and go this is correct rather than
this. And there's a lot of ideological
perspectives that people have which are
uh a bit problematic. And if you have so
much science refined around the idea of
it's bad to reject a nuance in a sense
um then it it at least uh it builds up
evidence for that that perspective. Um I
I also think that um it can it can help
in in structure societal change and a
predictive mechanism for people inside
uh debates with elites etc. Um, and
these things can add to a a betterment
of society and reducing the
polarization. But, uh, if we're talking
about uh the the changes of ideologies
with consideration to these things, I
think it'll only be uh if someone
considers what we're saying, uh, then
there's so much evidence behind it that
it it can show it's bad to be
absolutist. Basically, it's bad to not
be nuanced inside any direction anyone
takes. It encourages everybody, no
matter who it is, to be a bit more
nuanced and maybe Socratic and question
themsel and never be fully certain about
anything.
H how do you feel that that might come
into play
in our
discussions? like how would this how
would this
um for somebody let's just say
experiencing that
rigidity how would this land or what if
rigidity remains a viable cognitive
strategy even in light of knowing about
it like in almost a sort of cooperate
defect fashion like a global optima
could be reached with two flexible
parties but one rigid and one flexible
leads to a different outcome.
Yeah. Uh well, I I think uh if we're
talking about rigid inside the the
temperature dynamic, then it's good at
going down a path. Um but if there's the
option of both exploring and going down
that path, then it's very unlikely that
it's going to be correct. It's just
there's a statistically less chance. Uh
the the arguments of who will be better
inside any political dynamic, um that's
not really necessarily, you know, I
can't say either way. you know, it's
it's it's impossible to predict who's
going to be better in any situation, but
the probability that an unnuanced path
would be better is quite low because
it's it's a rejection of consideration
considering alternatives. It's not a
rejection of something because it could
be wrong. It's it's it's even if even if
like if you're considering alternatives,
you could still go down the same path,
but if you're just not considering
alternatives, you're just lowering your
chances of success. And that's that's
what I meant more by the rigid. And if
we have the assessment of the people in
power, then it's more treating
people like they have uh like if they
are overly rigid and they're, you know,
like in charge of of like Kim Jong-un in
charge of North Korea, it would give a
perspective of analyzing them not as a
rational party, but as someone who can
be predicted based off what they find is
important to them and what they're
likely to do on very uh narrow, rigid
circumstances.
It's uh you can probably give diagnostic
criteria for them of what they're likely
to consider in a lot of ways. And you
can also point out that because of their
rigidity and their lack of consideration
of alternatives, they're very unlikely
to act outside of very predictable
metrics according to the dynamics they
have chosen to act currently.
Yeah. Two two things that makes me think
of. First, the more templated or rigid a
given actor is, the more predictable
their behavior is in terms of their
sense making and decision selection,
which actually can be a strategic
detriment. So, open openness or
flexibility, it leaves leaves leaves the
possibility open for action that's
difficult to predict. Um and then also
when we start to see the reasoning type
models. So again to the sort of earlier
question of how do marovian generative
models come to capture
multi-stage reasoning like processes and
how do we model the duration of thinking
in behavior. basically this reflective
to
reflexive continuum.
Um the
more
rigid focusing just on the on a language
model example, the more rigid the
distribution of the next token, the less
thinking matters because it's just being
captured in small
attractors. Whereas the the larger the
vista for reasoning, the more
combinatorics and the more semantic
exploration can happen in that chain of
thought space. And so there can actually
be semantically important
considerations and kind of a space for
there to be adaptive updating.
So it's a and then there's a fundamental
trade-off because there's the time cost
of thinking and there's also like
rumination and so on. So there's no free
lunch. There's no general strategy that
can be you know in a system independent
way and and that's not what the
framework does. uh as you you basically
said with the with the political case as
well, it gives us these state spaces
where these very grand tradeoffs can be
elucidated and they apply importantly to
different scales of deliberation like
reflective and reflexive could be
happening to a given person or it could
be a group deliberative process. And so
that points the way to a very
interesting synthetic approach to
understanding the the first principles
of of biology and ourselves as
political.
Yeah. I mean 100%. Um it's the the the
idea of um exploration meaning that you
know you know you're in the exploratory
thing so there's more exploration that
the more thinking that happens and if
you're in a rigid thing the more
dramatic changes that happen I think is
is quite quite uh apt but um but it's
also interesting to consider that if you
are theoretically open to a plethora of
different options and you are exploring
quite a lot then you are also going to
have more of a normally
distributed perspective on things
whenever there are whenever there's a
chance of noise cancelling out. So, so
that that that sounds a bit odd, but
basically um when you have uh a massive
amount of exploration and you're
considering everything, sometimes you
can look the same as everyone else who
is considering everything. Even though
you are theoretically thinking more and
you're doing a lot more uh you you you
give the appearance of being you know
more predictable and and more of all
these things and and you probably are to
a degree just because you have a
normally distributed consideration of a
lot of different alternatives rather
than going down one absolute direction
then dramatic change to another absolute
direction. So there are there are issues
with that. Um but yeah uh the the the
reason why I was more interested in the
predictable elements of a of uh
authoritarians and their rigid mentality
is because you can uh through a nuanced
understanding of them give more of a
distinct prediction to them than you
could around someone who is exploring
all the things all the time and trying
to make accurate predictions of
everything through a non- rigid
mentality.
But and it's sort of the U-shaped curve,
the entropy curve returns again where in
in one game situation the same move is
always selected in the other. It's a
uniform distribution. In both cases,
while it's easier to predict the one
move player than the specific square,
you do know the distribution that the
uniform player is going to select. So
it's it it has a predictability but not
in detail like the one move player does.
And then in the middle are sort of
strategies that have all this different
complexity in terms of actually having
adaptive
possibility. Um yeah. So what are your
next moves or how could people provide
feedback or what are your what are you
looking to kind of get to next?
What are we looking to get to next? Um,
uh, well, integrate ourselves with the
active for influence community more. Um,
talk about as much development as we can
inside the area. Uh, we're very
interested in the writing of this book
that we have and and trying to get a
career in the the computational
neuroscience of politics, which would be
pretty interesting. But, uh, what well,
we're we're exploring all our options
and trying to help out people along the
way. Um I do like the idea of uh the
sophistication in game theory as the
predictable nature of of things. But I
think uh I think that there was an
interesting um study on on artificial
intelligence and general intelligence
and the deep learning of AI and it it
kind of showed that when they trained a
chessbot to predict one move ahead, it
was actually better than when they
changed a chessbot to predict it two
moves ahead except through five times
the amount of data. So there's a there's
a strange thing which is that
uh a higher level sophistication is more
like you're just trying to go into the
the chaos of the world. Whereas if you
try and do everything one step at a
time, a lot of the time it actually adds
out to something better.
Well, there's a a a joke we've had for
some years like active inference only
works for one time step, but you get to
do it again and again and you can load
everything into that time step, but you
only get one because if you were able to
plan out trajectories of multiple, it's
equivalent to saying that you had
already pre-imagined all of what you
could have received. And if you want to
do a roll out with all that you could
have received from your first action in
terms of all the ways that that could
influence your second
action, even with a small state space,
you're already getting into these absurd
rollouts. So that kind of is the
justification for having a action
perception loop that's ongoing, whether
it's called runtime or real time or
online inference or just active
inference. Even when people don't really
come at it from the free energy
principle side, they're just thinking
about online learning and about systems
that do active data sampling, those
kinds of processes. It kind of reaches
to the same place, which is like there
is information in the consequence of
action such that you don't know what
you're going to
do by taking two steps ahead like you
would by going one then one. And that's
operationally how it proceeds either
way. And that's the sort of paradox of
planning where planning is commonly
modeled going back to again same with
our chess metaphor. They're modeled as
these trees of different possibilities
and branching. But we know that that is
not what happens in the way that
planning proceeds
um or even if planning explicitly
proceeds in analog systems in the same
way. Yet it can be approximated with
this sort of branching counterfactual
play. However, in a one time step limit
is sort of where biological systems have
tuned themselves to.
Yeah, makes sense.
I think uh it's easier to think of
things in in uh in in exploitative terms
because there's less free energy. So
it's it's I think maybe people delude
themselves to thinking that they can
plan three steps ahead just because uh
it's I don't want to think about the
other steps anyway. I want to think
everything's this easy, but I don't
know. Yeah. Well, in a in a reward or
pragmatic value only setting, if you're
considering one time step at a time, you
do get greedy behavior. But then if you
have epistemic value as a real
contender, then you can still have
action selection reflecting learning in
that next time step because the expected
information gain is legitimately valued.
And so that can even say like well I
know that there's going to be a slight
benefit if I go down that gradient but
there might be other information if I go
up the gradient of pragmatic value and
so by bringing the information gain into
that next time step then at least
there's the possibility of of making
co-accounting for epistemic and
pragmatic value then that's exactly what
the kinds of
modifications and and attention
variations that you're describing get
I think so. Um I I I think there's
there's an interesting uh study which is
Axel Rod's study of tit and it kind of
showed that uh consideration of um uh if
you if you try and do the the prisoners
dilemma like over and over again then
you know the idea of there there's a you
know in a study where it's everyone says
the the best things you can do for
yourself is to focus on uh only doing
the thing that'll betray the other
person and and selfishly get you the
best points. And you should always
choose that option inside this prisoners
dilemma. But in in the study where they
did it 50 times in a row and it was
computer programming trying to do them
against each other, everyone thought
let's make the selfish bot which can try
and take advantage of the other people
cuz we're competing to try and who has
the best bot. And all the selfish bots
did a lot worse. It was uh the most
forgiving bots did the best. It was
people who did it better than a tit
fortat basis across all the examples of
interactions they went into. They did
the best. And it's
it's not that in each individual
situation they did the best because they
would have a bot which could either draw
or lose but across every interaction
their average amount of points was
always the best which kind of kind of
does show your thing about doing things
in a individual basis. You're doing it
one step at a time. Then that would be a
lot worse for you as an individual. But
if you have consideration to this
vaguely nuanced perspective of being
cooperative in society, being a
cooperative organization or a
cooperative country across all the
interactions you have, even if you're
not doing it, if you're doing it in a I
draw or I lose, because of the plethora
of good cooperative techniques you have
across all the situations you're in, you
do a lot better than someone who does
things
selfishly. And that's that's I think
very similar to that.
Totally totally agree.
Awesome. Yeah. It's also if you're
interested in global change game, it's a
this thing uh when they put people who
have very strong right-wing
authoritarianism into a game and it's a
4-hour simulation of controlling the
whole uh world. And um uh when they put
very strong uh super authoritarian
people inside the game altogether, they
started off giving each other wedgies,
wrote on a piece of paper, look after
your own, take care of your own type of
thing, and then they committed nuclear
war on each other. It was the worst game
they'd ever seen. They had to restarted
and then there was more nuclear war. And
in the opposite, when they had the least
authoritarian people in there, they
weren't, you know, going, I will bomb
you or you give me all your money type
of thing. They were going, let's try and
work together. Even though it was meant
to be a competitive game, they
apparently had the most cooperative game
they'd ever seen, even though 400,000
people in this world scale dynamic thing
still died. And it's it's an interesting
look at the reflection of how cognitive
rigidity because it's attached to
right-wing authoritarianism because the
the traits are being conventional,
authoritarian, authoritarian aggression,
submission, and conventionalism. uh
cognitive fragility is a strong factor
in how cooperative people are in
political dynamics and also how much
political dynamics can be reduced to
chaos
and yeah a lot of ways to go with that
but I mean your presentation and and
hopefully the forthcoming works
will bring some of that thinking out
more and I look forward to seeing. Thank
you. Thank you so much. Anything else
you want to say or ask?
Uh, no. I mean, it's been a pleasure.
Um, thank you for the opportunity. I'm
sorry if I didn't do the presentation
very well. I kind of sprinted through
quite a bit of things and and such, but
I really appreciated it. Thank you.
Yeah. Hope people enjoyed it and follow
up with the contact if they have any
additional comments they'd like to
provide and good luck with the work.
See you. Okay. Bye. Yeah.